<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks upon Dr. Sherlock's book, intituled, The case of the allegiance due to soveraign princes, stated and resolved, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Samuel, 1649-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220008</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2050:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks upon Dr. Sherlock's book, intituled, The case of the allegiance due to soveraign princes, stated and resolved, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Samuel, 1649-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 1 [i.e. 13], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at London, and re-printed in Edinburgh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Johnson by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Remarks upon Dr. Sherlock's case of allegiance.</note>
                  <note>Page 13 misnumbered 1.</note>
                  <note>Anonymous. By Samuel Johnson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Case of the allegiance due to soveraign powers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:35909:1"/>
REMARKS UPON Dr. <hi>SHERLOCK'S</hi> BOOK, Intituled, The CASE OF THE ALLEGIANCE DUE TO SOVERAIGN PRINCES, Stated and Reſolved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and Re-printed in <hi>Edinburgh, Anno Dom.</hi> 1691.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:35909:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35909:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REMARKS UPON D<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> SHERLOCK'S CASE of ALLEGIANCE, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAVING lately Peruſed <hi>Dr. Sherlock's Reaſons</hi> (as the Books is commonly called) I cannot forbear imparting to you ſome very few Obſervations upon them, not <hi>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſhew my Skill,</hi> but to perform my Promiſe.</p>
            <p>I obſerve in the Firſt place, That the <hi>Doctor</hi> thinks it <hi>neceſſary to convince all ſober Chriſtians, That men may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">pref. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſwear Allegiance to King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>without renouncing any Principles of the</hi> Church of England. But I hope we were not in ſuch a condition, as that <hi>All Sober Chriſtians</hi> ſtood in need of ſuch a Conviction. And God forbid the Principles of the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſhould be ſuch, as not only to create in <hi>all ſober Chriſtians,</hi> a doubt whether they might ſwear Allegiance to the Preſent <hi>King and Queen;</hi> but ſhould be ſo obſcure in the matter, as that ſo Learned a Man the <hi>Doctor</hi> is reputed, and ſo Wiſe a Man as he would be thought, <hi>(for he never gave any juſt occaſion to the world to mark him out for a fool),</hi> ſhould be at almoſt Two Years Pains to make a Reconciliation betwixt Them, and the Duty of Swearing Allegiance <note place="margin">Pref. p. 1.</note> to this preſent Government; upon the continuance of which the <hi>Doctor</hi> does more than once or twice acknowledge the Liberties and Religion of the Nation to depend.</p>
            <p>He confeſſes <hi>he ſtuck, and ſhould have ſtuck to this day, had he not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by Biſhop</hi> Overal's Convocation-Book; <hi>and had the Venerable Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pref. p. 5.</note> 
               <hi>of a Convocation given him greater Freedom and Liberty of Thinking, which the apprehenſions of Novelty and Singularity had cramp'd before:</hi> How mean are we Laymen in the eyes of theſe Gentlemen<hi>!</hi> Nothing that was done, ſaid, or writ, at and after the Revolution, to juſtifie the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof by the Laws of God and of this Realm, had any influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35909:3"/>
this <hi>Clergy man</hi>'s Judgment or Conſcience, till he met with a new upſtart <hi>Convocation-Book.</hi> Nay, his very Thoughts were in Chains, till <hi>the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Authority of a Convocation</hi> gave him <hi>Liberty to Think.</hi> What the Lords and Commons did, the Conſent of a Nation, the Approbation of all Proteſtants abroad, the Intereſt of Religion and the Publick Weal, were not conſiderable enough to give this man a liberty to <hi>think;</hi> his <hi>liberty of Thinking was cramp'd, till the Venerable Authority of a Convocation</hi> came and ſet him <hi>at liberty.</hi> I wonder the leſs to find him in his Book, enſlaving his Life and Liberty, to what, in a miſtaken Notion, he calls <hi>God's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> ſince I perceive his very Thoughts are ſlaves to an Aſſembly of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtiks.</p>
            <p>He waves the matter of <hi>Right,</hi> is not concerned in <hi>the Legality of the late Revolution,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">But I hope all Subjects that believe it, may and ought to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it. And upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would, if they did believe it; elſe they lye on the lurch.</note> 
               <hi>to diſpute ſhe Right of Princes, is a thing which no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can permit to be a queſtion amongſt their Subjects; ſuch Diſputes are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in this Cauſe, and ſerve only to confound it, by carrying men into ſuch dark Labyrinths of Law and Hiſtory,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as very few know how to find their way out again.</hi> To <hi>judge truly of the legality of the late Revolution, requires ſuch a perfect skill in Law and Hiſtory, and the Conſtitution of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government, that few men are capable of making ſo plain and certain a judgment of it, as to be a clear and ſafe Rule of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laymen</hi> think Laws and Conſtitutions of Governments to be <hi>ſafe Rules of Conſcience</hi> in theſe Caſes; and no ſuch <hi>dark Labyrinths</hi> as the Myſteries of the <hi>Holy Trinity and Incarnation,</hi> the <hi>Satisfaction of our Saviour,</hi> the <hi>Judge of Controverſies,</hi> &amp;c. which yet are all as plain to the <hi>Doctor,</hi> as a Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff; the <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> are admirably clear in all theſe things; but the <hi>Laws</hi> of a Nation, and the <hi>Conſtitution of its Government,</hi> are a <hi>dark Labyrinth. None are ſo blind as they that will not ſee.</hi> Till ſome Proud, Ambitious Clergy-men, and Flattering Courtiers, either really or pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ignorant of our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> ſet their own and other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Heads and Pens at work, to repreſent our Government in quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than its own native Colours, out of a baſe Compliance with a Court that left no ſtone unturn'd, to overthrow it; till then, I ſay, the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Government was ſo well underſtood by our Fore-fathers, that they ſupported and aſſerted it from time to time, at a vaſt Expence of Blood and Treaſure, and tranſmitted it down to their Poſterity, as they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from their Anceſtors, confirmed with all the Sanctions that the nature of the thing was capable of; nor were ever beholden to a <hi>Foreign Prince</hi> to preſerve it, till now; nor needed to have had recourſe to the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> to aſſert their Liberties, if the overflowing of ſuch <hi>Bigottry</hi> as this Gentleman is infected with, had not almoſt unmann'd the Nation, and prepar'd them for <hi>Slavery:</hi> And two ways were taken to effect it, the one, by perſwading us, That we are Slaves by the Law of God; and the other, by repreſenting our Government as being <hi>abſolute</hi> in its Original Conſtitution; and that whatever Liberties the People claim a Right to, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35909:3"/>
either Conceſſions from the <hi>Crown,</hi> or Uſurpations upon it. And becauſe ſome ignorant People have been impoſed upon by the miſapplication of <hi>Scripture</hi> by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and by miſ-underſtanding and miſ-applying our Ancient <hi>Hiſtories</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> and not thoroughly ſearching them neither, our Conſtitution and Fundamental Laws muſt now be repreſented as not clear, nor a ſafe Rule for Conſcience; and therefore another muſt be ſet up in ſtead of them, invented by a <hi>Clergy-man</hi> in his Study, directed in his Enquiry by a few of his own <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> either ignorant of our Conſtitution, or proſeſſed Enemies to it, or both; and this Rule of Conſcience, not ſo clear neither, but that our Spiritual Guides are together by the ears about it, and the Learned Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has been all this while finding it out: But found it he has: The Mountains have been in Labour, and behold the Mouſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God, when he ſees fit, and can better ſerve the Ends of his Providence by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">pag. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>it, ſets up Kings, without any regard to Legal Right, or Human Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Kings thus ſet up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by God, are inveſted with God's Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Subjects are bound to Obey, and to Pay and Swear Allegiance (if it be required) to thoſe Princes whom God hath placed and ſettled in the Throne, when they are inveſted with God: Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no new Invention of the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s, nor does he pretend to it; he had it (it ſeems) from <hi>Biſhop Overal's Convocation-Book.</hi> But Sir <hi>Robert Filmer</hi> broached it before that Book came out, in his <hi>Patriarcha;</hi> and that it will ſerve the turn of every <hi>Uſurper</hi> is evident, nor does the Doctor deny it.</p>
            <p>But that the Poſſeſſion of the Throne, and the actual Adminiſtration of a Government, creates a <hi>Right,</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> is poſitive in; not ſuch a <hi>Right</hi> as ſhall Entitle a King to be what we poor Lay-men call a <hi>King de Jure;</hi> but to be a <hi>Rightful King with reſpect to God:</hi> And why ſo? Why, becauſe <hi>the Moſt High Ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will, and ſetteth over it the baſeſt of Men. It is he that removeth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings. Shall there be evil in the City; and the Lord hath not done it? They are the Miniſters of God. All Power is of God; the Powers that be, are ordained of God. I exalted thee out of the duſt, and made thee Prince over my people Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I cannot underſtand the <hi>Doctor</hi>'s Inference from ſuch Expreſſions as theſe. That God governs the World, and that all things come to paſs by his Providence, I hope is paſt diſpute. And that ſuch expreſſions as theſe, are to be underſtood only of God's Ordinary Providence in the guidance of Humane Affairs, will perhaps appear by the common ſtyle of <hi>Scripture,</hi> in aſcribing all things of what kind or nature ſoever, natural or moral, good bad, immediately (in words) to the firſt Cauſe. God is ſaid to <hi>inſtruct the Plowman in diſcretion, and to teach him: And that his skill cometh from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa 28. 26, 29. Exod. 35. 31.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord of Hoſts, which is wonderful in counſel, and excellent in working. So God filled</hi> Bezaleel <hi>with the Spirit of God, in wiſdom, in underſtanding, and in knowledge, and in all manner of workmanſhip. Thunder</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>the Voice of God. God hardned</hi> Pharaoh<hi>'s heart. Is there evil in the City, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Job 40. 9.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35909:4"/>
               <hi>the Lord hath not done it?</hi> So God ſets up Princes, and removes them by <hi>the Events of Providence:</hi> But that their Authority is derived immediatly from God, or that they have, when ſetled in the Throne, any other <hi>Authority</hi> than what the Conſtitution of the Government allows, much leſs that they can have an <hi>Authority from God,</hi> in oppoſition to a <hi>Legal Right, I</hi> ſhall believe, when I ſee a Prince work greater Miracles, than Curing the King's Evil, to Juſtify the delegation of ſuch Authority.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctor,</hi> throughout this Diſcourſe, runs upon a notion of Mens Duty to <hi>Princes only,</hi> as if the Perſons of Princes were the <hi>ſole Objects</hi> of our Duty and Obedience; That is his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and proceeds from his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Nature of Humane Laws in Political Governments. It is a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſuits only with a Deſpotical Government, which is down-right Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; nor has the Doctor an Idea of any other: And if he had not been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly prejudiced againſt the Truth, by the ignorance of his Education in things of this nature, that excellent Diſcourſe of Mr, <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s, in anſwer to his Book of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> would have had another effect upon him than a ſcornful Reprinting of his own Book in anſwer to it.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Section is taken up with proving from Biſhop <hi>Overal's Book,</hi> That <hi>though the Church of</hi> England <hi>has been very careful to inſtruct her Children in their Duty to Princes; to obey their Laws, and ſubmit to their Power.</hi> and not to reſiſt, though very injuriouſly oppreſſed; <hi>and that thoſe who renounce theſe Principles, renounce the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England <hi>that ſhe takes care to condemn all thoſe wicked means whereby changes of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are made; yet ſhe teaches, that when ſuch changes are made, the Authority is God's, and muſt be obeyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we learn, that if this be the Doctrine of the <hi>Church</hi> of England; then by the Laws of God, as the <hi>Church</hi> of England underſtands them, and teaches them to her Children, all the People of <hi>England</hi> are <hi>Slaves.</hi> For to be <hi>injuriouſly oppreſsed,</hi> is to be oppreſſed <hi>contrary to Law; Executio Juris non habet injuriam;</hi> No Man can pretend that he or any body elſe is injured, when the Laws have their Courſe. But from <hi>very injurious oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> the true Sons of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have no redreſs, becauſe they muſt not reſiſt the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which the <hi>Prince Regnant</hi> is inveſted with. Whatever the Conſtitution of the Government be, whatever Laws your Forefathers have provided for the continuance and preſervation of it; whatever <hi>Legal Right</hi> you may fancy you have to your <hi>Lives, Liberties, Religion, Properties;</hi> if you aſſert and defend this <hi>Legal Right</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>very injurious oppreſsions</hi> of your <hi>Princes,</hi> who in a <hi>Limited Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> (as yours is acknowledged to be) have but a <hi>limited</hi> Power by Law; yet in ſo doing you oppoſe the <hi>Authority of God:</hi> And ſo your Laws are but Cobwebs; your <hi>Legal Right,</hi> an Imaginary Notion: Your Princes have an <hi>Authority from God</hi> to cancel your Laws, and diſpoſe of you and your Rights as they ſee Cauſe. Thus by the Doctrine of your <hi>Church</hi> (as this Gentleman Repreſents it) you are in no better a condition, than if you were Subjects to the <hi>Grand Seignior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35909:4"/>
Your Forefathers, (who fought for your Liberties, in oppoſition to the Tyranny of K, <hi>John,</hi> K, <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>3d,</hi> K. <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>2d,</hi> &amp;c. and who, if they had acknowledged ſuch an irreſiſtible Authority of their Princes, as the Doctor contends for, and had not vindicated the Government by force of Arms, you their Poſterity had long before now been in the ſame, or a worſe condition than the Peaſants of <hi>France)</hi> were all <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebels,</hi> tho warranted by the Laws of the Land to make oppoſition, nay, and ſworn ſo to do by the <hi>King</hi>'s own Commiſſion, as particularly in the Reign of King <hi>John.</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the third. This Notion of an <hi>Irreſiſtible Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> in your Princes, becauſe they have <hi>Gods Authority,</hi> was not then hatch'd: nor did it appear in the World till the degeneracy of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brought it forth<hi>:</hi> For Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Parliaments and Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were of another Opinion: as has been proved by many Inſtances of their giving her Subſidies to relieve diſtreſſed Subjects againſt their own Princes<hi>:</hi> and when <hi>Sibthorp</hi> and <hi>Manwaring</hi> broached thoſe Traiterous Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt his time, they were impeached in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſeverely cenſured for it. Yet notwithſtanding all, this Clergy-man will have it to be the Doctrine of the Church; which if it were purſued, does una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably deſtroy the State; and therefore by his own Argument <hi>(pag.</hi> 44) can be no good Doctrine; becauſe, if purſued, it would ſubject all Human Societies to be deſtroyed; whereas he acknowledges the End of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be the preſervation of Human Societies. And he has the aſſurance to publiſh his Conceits of this kind, under a Government, that has been happily ſetled amongſt us in oppoſition to, and in ſpight of theſe ſlaviſh Conceits of ſome of our Clergy. A Government, which thoſe who contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to erect, this Doctor brands with the loudeſt Calumnies<hi>:</hi> and yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which he now ſeeks protection, and which he acknowledges now at laſt, being convinc'd thereof by the <hi>Events of Providence,</hi> to have the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God, though introduced by the Devil.</p>
            <p>But how does it follow, that this Doctrine of his muſt therefore be receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of</hi> England? becauſe he finds it in <hi>Biſhop</hi> Overal<hi>'s Book.</hi> Do the <hi>Canons</hi> of a <hi>Convocation,</hi> neither aſſented to by <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> nor ſo much as by the King<hi>'s Letters-Patents,</hi> make, or authoritatively declare the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? Is</hi> the <hi>Convocation</hi> the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Body of the <hi>Church</hi> of England; (I know they tell us ſo in the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1603. But I never found that any but ſome few of the <hi>Clergy</hi> believed them) Has what he calls the <hi>Church,</hi> a power to determine matters of <hi>Civil Right?</hi> Are we to go to School to <hi>Clergy-men</hi> to learn the Terms and Meaſures of our <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to <hi>Magiſtrates;</hi> which all Mankind, but a few of that profeſſion in our own Nation, acknowledge to depend upon Human Laws, and the ſeveral Conſtitutions of Government, and which the body of our <hi>Clergy</hi> are ſo ignorant of, that they are a <hi>dark Labyrinth</hi> to them. <hi>When the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the ditch.</hi> And yet his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument <note place="margin">Page 9, 10,</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35909:5"/>
drawn from the pretended <hi>Canons</hi> of that <hi>Convocation, are as good Authority as can be urged to the Members of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>for if a Convocation cannot declare the Judgement of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>he knows not where we ſhall learn it.</hi> So that the Members of the <hi>Church of</hi> England are to be guided in matters relating to their <hi>Temporal Rights,</hi> by an Aſſembly of their <hi>Clergy:</hi> Though even our Popiſh Anceſtors proteſted from time to time againſt the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome in Temporalibus.</hi> But I can tell him whence, and whence only he may learn the Doctrine and Judgment of the <hi>Church of England</hi> authoritatively; <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Articles</hi> and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> which have the publick Sanction of the <hi>Legiſlative Authority;</hi> not in his Spurious <hi>Canons</hi> of 1610, nor in thoſe of 1640, nor yet in the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> though appointed by Act of Parliment to be read in Churches; for ſo is the <hi>Apocrypha;</hi> and yet we do not ſubmit to thoſe Books as <hi>Authoritative.</hi> All other writings are but the Opinions of private Men,</p>
            <p>The reſt of that Section conſiſts of ſome Stories of <hi>Jehu, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezebel;</hi> The <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Aramites, Ehud</hi> and <hi>Eglon,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Four Monarchs, Alexander, Darius, Jaddus,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar.</hi> All which are no more to us, than if he had told us a tale of <hi>Tom Thumb, or Guy of Warwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is no new thing for the <hi>Clergy</hi> to top Foreign Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon us; One of their <hi>Canons</hi> in 1603. is, <hi>Quicunque in poſterum aſſirmabit Poteſtatem Regiam non habere eandem Authoritatem in Cauſis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis, quam Pii Principes apud Judeos &amp; Chriſtiani Imperatores in Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiva Eccleſiâ obtinuerunt, &amp;c. Excommunicetur ipſo facto, &amp;c.</hi> Our King's Juriſdiction in matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> is ſetled and bounded by Laws of this Realm; and thoſe Laws we look upon as the meaſure of their Authority. But <hi>Clergy men</hi> make nothing of Human Laws, at leaſt not of the <hi>Laws of</hi> England; But ſend us to the <hi>Jews</hi> and to the <hi>Romans,</hi> to enquire what Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority their Princes had, and very boldly determine, under the penalty of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> That <hi>Our Kings</hi> have <hi>eandem poteſtatem:</hi> And yet they neither know what power <hi>our Laws</hi> allow to <hi>our Kings,</hi> nor what <hi>their Laws</hi> allow'd to <hi>theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He grants, that <hi>Kings ſet up by God, have God's Authority;</hi> and that <hi>all Kings who are in the actual poſſeſsion of the Government, are ſet up by God:</hi> And therefore having <hi>God's Authority, Allegiance</hi> is due to them. So that he reſolves the Duty of <hi>Allegiance</hi> into the Authority committed by God to the Prince; the committing of which Authority appears by the <hi>Events of Providence.</hi> For <hi>Providence is God's Government of the World by an inviſible Influence and Power; the Ends of which he ſerves by overruling mens wicked Deſigns to accompliſh his own Counſels and decrees, and either diſappoints what they intended, or gives ſucceſs to them, when he can ſerve the Ends of his Providence by their wickedneſs.</hi> But how ſhall Subjects judge when God ſerves the ends of his Providence by man's wickedneſs, and conſequently <hi>when their obedience becomes due to a new Prince? why, obedience is due to God's</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35909:5"/>
               <hi>authority, when we can reaſonably conclude that God has made him King:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">p. 16.</note> That is, <hi>when the providence of God has ſettled him in the Throne. But there are different degrees of ſettlement, which require different degrees of ſubmiſsion.</hi> The Doctor has gone hand in hand with providence ever ſince the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <note place="margin">p. 17.</note> 
               <hi>The generality of the Nation ſubmitted to the preſent King and Queen and placed them on the Throne, and put the whole power of the Kingdom into their hands, though it may be the Doctor could not think them ſettled by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedence,</hi> whileſt the late King <hi>had ſuch a formidable power as made the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">p. 17.</note> 
               <hi>doubtful, yet becauſe he thought fit to continue in the Kingdom, he could live quietly and peaceably, pay taxes, give them the title of King and Queen, and pray for them as ſuch, becauſe we are bound to pray for all that are in authority,</hi> and that their Majeſties had, <hi>becauſe they had power to do a great deal of good or a great deal of hurt. Here power to do good or harm</hi> is authority<hi>:</hi> And Thieves and Robbers have that. But it may be the King and Queen had <hi>Gods authority</hi> all this while, before the <hi>Doctor</hi> thought fit to own it by ſwearing Allegiance to them; becauſe he did not know they had it, <hi>till the power of the dipoſſeſſed Prince was broken, and no viſible proſpect of his recovering his Throne again.</hi> So that men of the <hi>Doctor's</hi> opinion muſt watch till God has play'd his game out; before they can be aſcertain'd what his will and pleaſure is in theſe matters of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſwearing Allegiance to <hi>Princes:</hi> For the will of God, when known, is the rule of Conſcience. But the will of God in theſe caſes is no otherwiſe to be known but by the <hi>Events of Providence.</hi> So that men of ſuch Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as this Gentleman repreſents to us for <hi>Church of England</hi> Principles, muſt ſtay till the Storm be over, and then they'l tell us 'tis fair weather. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſufficiently expreſs my indignation againſt men that can have the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to repreſent the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which is the body of the People of <hi>England,</hi> and who have a right to their <hi>Properties, and Religion</hi> as far as theſe words, <hi>Right to Properties and Religion</hi> can be extended, as a ſort of men who muſt not ſtir their finger in oppoſition to a Prince that invades this Right all at once, upon a ſuppoſition that the Prince is inveſted with <hi>God's Authority;</hi> as if a man could act by <hi>God's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Laws of the Realm,</hi> and his own Oath to obſerve them, and cauſe them to be duly executed; as if Princes had any other <hi>Authority</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> then to <hi>govern according to Law;</hi> as if reſiſting a <hi>Lawleſs Authority,</hi> which is no Authority, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the <hi>Authority of God;</hi> as a ſort of men to whom the Laws and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the Nation, upon which all that can be <hi>dean</hi> to us depends, muſt never owe any thing for their preſervation, tho' in the greateſt extremities, ſo long as they are guided by <hi>the ſpirit of their Church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (tho' thanks be to Heavens a late Divine has furniſhed us with a diſtinction betwixt that and <hi>the ſpirit of God;)</hi> No, they muſt be quiet and ſuffer all to be trampled underſoot by <hi>God's Authority,</hi> unleſs <hi>wicked-men</hi> form <hi>deſigns</hi> againſt <hi>God's</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. Hick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note> 
               <hi>Authority</hi> to preſerve the Authority of the Laws and the Profeſſion of God's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35909:6"/>
true Religion<hi>:</hi> So that the beſt things that can be done in the World muſt be done by <hi>wicked men,</hi> and in oppoſition to <hi>God's Authority,</hi> or not be done at all. And all this while that the Church maſt ſit ſtill, the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God is at work by means of the Devil and his Agents, <hi>wicked men,</hi> againſt his own Authority, which a King that has a legal title, but exerciſes an illegal power, is inveſted with; <hi>and herein conſiſts the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wiſdom of Providence that God ſerves his own Ends by their Wickedneſs.</hi> It ſeems he can never ſerve his Ends by the Godlineſs of the Church; but muſt carry on Ends for their good, by the free Miniſteries of <hi>wicked men.</hi> All you Patriots, that with the hazard of your Lives and Eſtates ſtept into the gap to prevent <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> coming in like a torrent upon Church and State, and who in ſo doing thought you did God good Service, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your End was the preſervation of your own and your Countries Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Properties and Religion under a legal adminiſtration of the ancient Engliſh Government, were all that while ſighting againſt God, you were reſiſting the power ordain'd by God, and ſo doing you receiv'd to your ſelves damnation; and tho' God has wrought a deliverance through your wickedneſs, no thanks to you; tho' the Nation has conſented to what you have done by as univerſal a conſent as perhaps was ever heard of, this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional conſent is but an indication that God has given the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> his Authority, but does not inveſt them with any <hi>legal Right,</hi> that remains in the diſpoſſeſſed King yet<hi>:</hi> So that you and the Nation have but been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to transfer what it is not in your power to transfer, viz. a <hi>legal Right:</hi> And you have transferred what you never intended to transfer nor ever acknowledged; viz. an <hi>irreſiſtible Authority from God:</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has found out now what you were then doing, and ſees the conſequence of your Actions, to your ſelves and all men elſe unknown. You aided the Prince and promoted the Ends of his Declaration, which were to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Nation from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery, ſo as it might never be in the power of any Prince hereafter to introduce either:</hi> but Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> tells ye, that can never be done, for it never will be Lawful nor indeed poſſible to exclude <hi>Slavery:</hi> Becauſe every Prince has God's authority, which is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible, and I'm ſure he that is your Prince, and is by the Law of God ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible, to him you are ſlaves by the <hi>Law of God.</hi> So that you have but changed Maſters according to his principle, one of a rough temper, for a more mild one<hi>:</hi> And all your ſecurity depends upon the good nature of your Prince for the time being.</p>
            <p>I neither have leaſure, nor if I had that, can I have patience, nor, if I had both, can I think it worth my while to run through the Book, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madvert upon it <hi>Paragraph</hi> by <hi>Paragraph:</hi> For if it were much better writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten then it is, yet the writing of him, who ſlights and deſpiſes to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that he does upon all occaſions every man's reaſon but his own, and in this Diſcourſe ſets up an <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of his own for a Rule to men's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in matters of Government, without any regard to the Laws of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35909:6"/>
Nation can hardly deſerve ſo much regard as a ſerious anſwer would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>He tells us that <hi>an Oath to a diſpoſſeſſed Prince ceaſes</hi> Geſſante materiâ; <hi>for though the man be ſtill in being; the King is gone.</hi> So that the Kingly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <note place="margin">p. 16.</note> may be transferr'd from one perſon to another, But then they that aſſiſt and defend the new Prince in oppoſition to the title of him that is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed, muſt (I hope) not for the future <hi>abhor that treaſonable Doctrine and Poſition of levying War by the King's authority againſt his perſon.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He tells us <hi>the Scripture makes no diſtinction between Rightful Kings and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">pag. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Uſurpers: The Rule is general;</hi> Let every Soul be Subject to the higher powers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor does the Scripture define to us, who theſe higher Powers are<hi>:</hi> And I'm ſure they are not the ſame every where; In what perſon or perſons the Powers lodge, which here are ſaid to be ordain'd of God, and with what degree of Power they are inveſted, depends upon the ſeveral Conſtitutions of Governments; for if it be equally <hi>reſiſting God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> to Reſiſt <hi>all Princes</hi> without diſtinction; then I know no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt an <hi>abſolute</hi> and a <hi>limited</hi> Monarchy: then Princes have ſome dormant Authority or other, which the Laws does not give 'em: Which are Principles of ſlavery peculiar to this laſt Age, and to ſome of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Clergy.</p>
            <p>He will not have <hi>St. Paul to be underſtood of lawful powers only, for then it would be neceſſary for Subjects to examine the titles of Princes, which would involve the Conſciences of men in perplexitie; for theſe are diſputes amongſt learned men, and he cannot think that the reſolution of Conſcience in matters that all mankind are concerned in, ſhould depend upon ſuch niceiies as learned men themſelves cannot agree in.</hi> He will hardly allow this Poſition, with reference to matters of Religion, which yet I think all mankind are or ſhould be concerned in. Nor ought a rule to be rejected upon a ſuppoſition that it is not clear, becauſe learned Men differ about it; unleſs at the ſame time a New One be ſet up, which all learned Men doe agree in But the diſputes about Government are various, and that amongſt very learned men; and yet to the beſt of my Obſervation, all Men hitherto learned and unlearned have agreed that the Laws of a Nation, and the Conſtitution of it's Government are at leaſt a ſafe, a true rule for Conſcience<hi>:</hi> which if we ſhall leave and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſome <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> of a Schollar's Invention, I know not whether it may lead us at laſt.</p>
            <p>The Laws of a Nation may be trampled under foot, and it's Conſtitution broken by an inundation of Foreigners; this is a force, and a force gives no right, let the Doctor tell us to the world's end of <hi>All things being equally rightful with reſpect to God:</hi> men that are under a force, have a Right from Self-preſervation, which is a Law of Nature and conſequently of God, to rid themſelves of that force it they can. Conqueſts end, when the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Conquered come to mutual Pacts and Agreements, which are the Laws by which they agree to rule and be ruled for the future. Till ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35909:7"/>
Pacts intervene, the Conquered People ſhift for themſelves as well as they can: But where there is no pretence nor appearance of any Conqueſt, where the Laws of a Nation, which are the publick Agreement of all the nation for their mutual defence and ſecurity retain their force; they cannot be good ſubjects, who ſet up any other rule of conſcience in matters of civil Right, Property or power: for that other rule is either agreeable with the Law, and then we need it not; or it is contrary to it, and then they that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it, are enemies to the Conſtitution. I know little difference betwixt aſſuming an authority to govern the State, and ſetting up other rules then that of the Law to guide men's Conſciences by in matters of Allegiance and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the civil Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Saviour's argument relies wholly on poſſeſsion of power?</hi> whoſe Image <note place="margin">pag. 21.</note> and ſuperſcription hath it? If ſuch a poſſeſſion as having the <hi>Coynage of Mony</hi> requires <hi>Allegiance,</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> ought to have taken the Oaths when the new money came out. If not, then our Saviour's argument does not <hi>juſtifie</hi> him now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We have no directions in Scripture about reſtoring a diſpoſſeſsed Prince to his Throne again</hi> But if the <hi>diſpoſſeſſed Prince retain a Legal right,</hi> then we are <note place="margin">pag. 22.</note> directed to reſtore him, <hi>Rom</hi> cap. 13. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Render unto all their dues, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to whom tribute is due, cuſtom to whom cuſtom, fear to whom fear, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to whom honour.</hi> If the <hi>late King</hi> have a <hi>legal right to the Crown,</hi> he has a <hi>legal right</hi> to the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> the <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Hearth money,</hi> &amp;c. And if he has a <hi>legal right</hi> to them, they are <hi>due</hi> to him. And if they are <hi>due</hi> to him, we are commanded to <hi>render them</hi> to him. And that the <hi>late King</hi> may yet have a <hi>legal right</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> the <hi>Doctor</hi> agrees. <hi>The Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God removes Kings and ſets up Kings, but alters no</hi> legal Rights. We are commanded <hi>to do as we would be done by;</hi> and none of us would be deprived our ſelves of our own <hi>legal Rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>late Kings</hi> have a <hi>legal Right</hi> yet, then no <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſubjects can have a <hi>legal Right</hi> to oppoſe him; unleſs a man can have a <hi>legal Right</hi> to an Eſtate, and at the ſame time another have a <hi>legal Right</hi> to with-hold it from him; which is to make the Law a contradiction to it ſelf; and yet theſe are neceſſary conſequences of the Doctors <hi>Poſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That one Prince is at preſent placed in the Throne, and the other removed out of it, does not diveſt the diſpoſſeſſed Prince of his legal right and claim, nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">pag. 26.</note> 
               <hi>forbid him to endeavour to recover his Throne, nor ſobid thoſe, who are under no obligation to the Prince in poſſeſsion, to aſsiſt the diſpoſſeſſed Prince to recover his legal Right: A Legal and ſucceſsive Right bars all other Humane Claims;</hi> ſo that the <hi>diſpoſſeſſed Prince</hi> has a juſt cauſe of War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Prince in poſſeſsion</hi> for the recovery of his <hi>Legal Right.</hi> And they that are under <hi>no obligation to the Prince in poſſeſsion,</hi> are not forbid to aſſiſt him: Who theſe are that are ſuppoſed to be under no obligation; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I know not. I hope if the Prince in poſſeſſion be <hi>throughly ſettled,</hi> he has <hi>God's Authority,</hi> and then all that are his Subjects are under ſome <hi>obligation</hi> to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35909:7"/>
him, or elſe <hi>God's Authority</hi> ſtands for nothing. But if foreign Princes are meant by <hi>thoſe who are under no obligation,</hi> then at leaſt the King of <hi>France</hi> has a juſt cauſe of War upon us to reſtore King <hi>James:</hi> And then at whoſe Doors muſt the Blood lie that is ſpilt in the War? If the late King have a legal Right, he has a Right by our Laws; and then in oppoſing his Title, we fight againſt our own Laws and Government. If the late King have a Legal Right to the Crown, then a man muſt be very learned indeed to be of opinion that the obligation of our Oaths of Allegiance to him, ceaſes. It is not enough for the <hi>Doctor</hi> to ſay, That <hi>it was neceſſary for him to reaſon upon the ſuſpicion of unjuſt Uſurpations, and illegal Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that he was far from intending to reflect upon the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. With Reverence be it ſpoken,</hi> is a common laying with ſome, when they are going to ſpeak blaſphemy. His ſtanding out ſo long, the grounds of his preſent compliance, his avowed Principles in his Book of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> which he here juſtifies excepting in one <hi>punctilio,</hi> ſhew un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyably that the <hi>Doctor</hi> acknowledges no other Right in Their Preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties, but an Authority from God of his own inventing; and that their only firm ſecurity, becauſe only ſatisfactory to the Conſciences of their Subjects, that of a Legal Right, which indeed is God's Authority, (and we acknowledge no other in theſe matters,) is by this Writer, as far as in him lyes, quite blown up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The duty of Subjects is to obey their Prince whilſt in poſsesſion; but Kings</hi> 
               <note place="margin">pag. 27.</note> 
               <hi>muſt take care to preſerve their Crowns by good Government: For if they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly violate their Subjects Rights,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it is too much to venture their lives and Fortunes, to keep them in the Throne to oppreſs them.</hi> But why ſhould not Subjects be obliged in Conſcience to defend ſuch an injurious Prince? He has a <hi>Legal Title, Poſſesſsion, a Settlement,</hi> he has <hi>God's Authority,</hi> he is <hi>irreſiſtible,</hi> and has the <hi>Soveraign Power.</hi> And is it no part of <hi>Soveraign Power</hi> to command the ſervice of his Subjects? No, he is entituled only to a <hi>legal defence,</hi> the <hi>Militia,</hi> and the <hi>Poſse Com.</hi> Thus when men are at <note place="margin">pag. 30.</note> a pinch, they ſeek refuge where they can. When their Doctrine of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> and a thouſand other aſcriptions to the power of the Prince turns upon them, they ſhelter themſelves under the <hi>Law</hi> of the Realm; Which when things go as they would have them go, they ſubject to the Prince's pleaſure<hi>:</hi> And to excuſe their taking ſhelter under what they have ſo baſely betrayed, they tell us tho' they taught <hi>Non-Reſiſtance;</hi> they may practice <hi>Non-Asſiſtance</hi> without forgoing that Doctrine. So they may ſuffer <hi>the Lord's Anointed, the light of their Eyes, and the breath of their Noſtrils to be taken in the pits of wicked Men,</hi> when he does not ſerve their turn, and be good Loyaliſts, good Church of <hi>England</hi> men, good King's men for all that. <hi>Quo teneam vultus mutantem Protea nodo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Doctrine of Obedience and Allegiance to the preſent powers is founded on the ſame principle with the Doctrine of</hi> Non-reſiſtance <hi>and</hi> Paſſive Obe-obedience. <note place="margin">pag. 36.</note> How the Doctor new moulds the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35909:8"/>
&amp;c. to ſquare with his <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> I am not concerned to trouble my ſelf about. I cannot but wonder that any good ſtream ſhould iſſue from ſo corrupt a Fountain, as that Doctrine (ſo as it was lately preached up and inculcated) proceeded from. But as that Doctrine was taught of late, the Argument muſt run thus, <q>Becauſe the late King <hi>Charles</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> had received a <hi>Soveraign Authority</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> which muſt be obeyed and not reſiſted, tho' the latter be now <hi>de facto</hi> deprived of the exreciſe of that Authority by Rebellious Subjects, aided by a Foreign Prince, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh their wicked enterpriſe, which does not diveſt the ſaid late King <hi>James</hi> of a Legal Right to recover it again; Therefore <hi>I</hi> do ſwear Faith and true Allegiance to their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs over many things that are ſo obvious, as not to deſerve a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Obſervation; as the contradiction he is guilty of, in telling us, that <hi>he could never find the Scriptures made any difference between Lawful and Uſurped Powers,</hi> and yet that <hi>he ſtuck, and had ſtuck to this day, had he not been relieved by Biſhop</hi> Overal<hi>'s Book;</hi> though all the help that Book could give him, was by helping him over that diſtinction. <hi>Oportet Menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem eſſe memorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing is the New-coyn'd account he gives of a <hi>limited Monarchy,</hi> viz. that in a <hi>limited Monarchy</hi> we are bound <hi>not to reſiſt,</hi> only we are not bound to <hi>aſsiſt.</hi> The ſaucy introducing of private men's whimſies into Schemes of Government in oppoſition to Laws of Nations, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe of mankind, has been obſerved before. But let the <hi>Doctor</hi> here take notice of an Expreſſion of a far greater Man than himſelf, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the true notion of a <hi>limited Government: Ubi Rex ſummam po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatem non habet, ſed partem alteram populus aut Senatus, Regi in partem non ſuam involanti vis juſta opponi poterit, quia eatenùs non eſt ſuperior.</hi> Grot. de jure Belli &amp; Pacis.</p>
            <p>He takes a great deal of pains to diſtinguiſh betwixt the preſent Caſe, and that of the late times under the <hi>Long Parliament, Oliver Cromwel,</hi> &amp;c and it is very obſervable how he gets over it upon his Principle. Why, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Nation was then quite overwhelmed; we had no <hi>King,</hi> nor <hi>Lords,</hi> and but <hi>a part of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> who carried all <hi>by force.</hi> And what then, I hope <hi>there were Powers in Being;</hi> and if ſo, they were of God, tho uſurped <hi>But there was not a Settlement,</hi> I know not what he calls a Settlement; the <hi>High-landers</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> were ſubdued, <hi>Ireland</hi> quite <hi>reduced,</hi> the Government then in being, ſuch as it was, acknowledged by all the Princes and Governments of Chriſtendom, nor was there then a Powerful Prince that waged War againſt the then Powers in behalf of the then diſpoſſeſſed Prince. But the truth of the difference is this, <hi>the then Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were no freinds to the Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When men are once out of the right way, they wander in various by paths, and ſo <hi>the Doctor, Hobbs, Filmer,</hi> &amp;c. leaving the Law of the Land, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35909:8"/>
is an agreement betwixt all Subjects, and flying to other notions of <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>God's Authority,</hi> and the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and no body knows what, may pleaſe themſelves with the Wit and Novelty of their own Speculations, but <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded will never find the Body of the People influenced by what ſuch Learned muſt be at ſo much pains to find out, and dreſs up with any tolerable appearance of ſenſe</p>
            <p>The Doctor is much concerned to free God from any confinement to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Laws: But ſince he would not have men violate them, he ought (I ſhould think) to ſhew that in taking the preſent Oaths he has not done it himſelf: Tho God is not confined to Human Laws, I do not know how the Events of his Providence can juſtifie men's breaking them, and their own former Oaths both at once. They that come into the intereſt of this preſent Government, upon the true Legal Foundation, upon which it ſtands, have broken neither. But how to entertain the Doctor's imaginary Hypotheſis of a Divine Authority, in oppoſition to a Legal Right: which is to make the Government of Divine Inſtitution, and yet contrary to Law: How to make it ſafe for King and People upon his Bottom, <hi>I</hi> know not, nor ſhall enquire any Father.</p>
            <q>God made man uprght, but he hath found out many inventions.</q>
            <q>To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
